Lesson 27 The 'Vasa'
"瓦萨"号
First listen and then answer the following question.
听录音,然后回答以下问题.
What happened to the 'Vasa' almost immediately after she was launched?
"瓦萨"号刚启航就发生了什么事情?
From the seventeenth-century empire of Sweden,
从17世纪瑞典帝国
galleon: n.  大型帆船
the story of a galleon that sank at the start of her maiden voyage in 1628
有个流传至今的故事,说是1628年,一艘大帆船在处女航开始时就沉没了,
must be one of the strangest tales of the sea.
这无疑是航海史上最离奇的事件之一.
Stockholm: n.  斯德哥尔摩
For nearly three and a half centuries she lay at the bottom of Stockholm harbour
这艘大船在期德歌尔摩港口的海底躺了将近3个世纪,
until her discovery in 1956.
直到1956年才被发现.
flagship: n.  旗舰
This was the Vasa, royal flagship of the great imperial fleet.
这就是"瓦萨"号,帝国大舰队的皇家旗舰.
King Gustavus Adolphus 'The Northern Hurricane',
号称"北方飓风"的国王古斯塔夫斯.阿道尔弗,
then at the height of his military success in the 'Thirty Years' War,
当时正处在"三十年战争" 的军事鼎盛阶段,
armament: n.  军械
had dictated her measurements and armament.
他亲自规定了这艘船的规模和武器配备.
mount: v.  架有, bronze: n.  青铜, cannon: n.  加农炮
Triple gun-decks mounted sixty-four bronze cannon.
3层的火炮甲板上装着64门青铜加农炮,
She was intended to play a leading role in the growing might of Sweden.
目的就是要在不断增长的瑞典势力中起主导作用.
As she was prepared for her maiden voyage on August 10, 1628,
1628年8月10日,"瓦萨"号准备首航时,
Stockholm: n.  斯德哥尔摩
Stockholm was in a ferment.
斯德歌尔摩一片欢腾.
From the Skeppsbron and surrounding islands
人们从斯开波斯布朗和周围的岛屿aa
the people watched this thing of beauty
前来观看这艘美丽的战船
begin to spread her sails and catch the wind.
扬帆起航,乘风前进.
They had laboured for three years to produce this floating work of art;
瑞典人辛辛苦苦干了3年才建成这件水上艺术品,
she was more richly carved and ornamented than any previous ship.
它比以往任何船只雕刻得都更加精美,装饰得都更加华丽.
The high stern castle was a riot of carved gods,demons,knights, kings,warriors,
高耸的船楼上雕刻着令人眼花缭乱的神仙,妖魔,骑士,国王,武士,
mermaids,cherubs;and zoomorphic animal shapes ablaze with red and gold and blue,
美人鱼和小天使,还有用红色,金黄色,蓝色绘制的光彩夺目的兽形图案,
symbols of courage, power,and cruelty,
象征着勇敢、力量和残暴,
were portrayed to stir the imaginations of the superstitious sailors of the day.
以激起当时崇尚迷信的水手们的想象.
cannon: n.  加农炮
Then the cannons of the anchored warships thundered a salute to which the Vasa fired in reply.
这时,停泊在港口的其他战船向"瓦萨"号鸣炮致礼,"瓦萨"号也鸣炮回礼.
As she emerged from her drifting cloud of gun smoke
当"瓦萨"号从弥漫的礼炮烟去中出现时,
with the water churned to foam beneath her bow,
船头下浪花四溅,
her flags flying, pennants waving, sails filling in the breeze,
舰旗迎风招展,三角旗随风飘动,微风鼓起风帆,
and the red and gold or her superstructure ablaze with colour,
金碧辉煌的船楼闪耀着灿烂的色彩.
Stockholm: n.  斯德哥尔摩
she presented a more majestic spectacle than Stockholmers had ever seen before.
"瓦萨"号展现的壮观景象是斯德歌尔摩人从未见过的.
All gun-ports were open and the muzzles peeped wickedly from them.
船上的炮眼都开着,炮口虎视眈眈地向外窥视着.
As the wind freshened there came a sudden squall and the ship made a strange movement, listing to port.
当风力增强时,突然刮来阵大风,瓦萨号奇怪地摇晃了一下便向左舷倾斜.
cannon: n.  加农炮
The Ordnance officer ordered all the port cannon to be heaved to starboard to counteract the list but the steepening angle of the decks increased.
炮长命令把左舷上所有大炮搬到右舷上来以抵消船的倾斜,但甲板的倾斜度仍在增加.
Then the sound of rumbling thunder reached the watchers on the shore,
然后岸上的观众听到船上发出了雷鸣般的轰响,
as cargo,ballast, ammunition and 400 people
原来是物品、压舱物、弹药和400个人
went sliding and crashing down to the port side of the steeply listing ship.
轰地一声滑向了陡斜的左舷.
The lower gun-ports were now belew water and the inrush sealed the ship's fate.
此时下层炮眼已淹没在水里,涌进船舱的水给瓦萨号带来了难以逃脱的厄运.
In that first glorious hour,the mighty Vasa, which was intended to rule the Baltic,
就这样,想要统治波罗的海的大型战舰"瓦舰"号,
sank with all flags flying--in the harbour of her birth.
在它壮丽的起航时刻,带着全身飘扬的彩旗,沉没在了它诞生的港口.